Okay, so in this video then we're going to
talk about the Tuckman model.
Now the Tuckman model then was a model of
team development, five stages of team
development, and it was developed by Bruce
Tuckman.
Now it's called either the Tuckman model,
sometimes it's referred
to as the Tuckman Ladder.
And he basically developed
this theory and he's basically
talking about the different
stages of team development, right?
These are the five
basic stages that a team
is going to go through
in their development.
Now, don't necessarily think of this just
as a team in an office environment.
I mean, it does include that, but it can
also include a group of team members,
a group of people, they've come together,
they don't know one another, right?
There are a group of strangers and even in
the middle of nowhere, right?
And these are the five
basic stages that the
team that the group
is going to go through.
So the stages are forming, storming,
norming, performing, and adjourning.
All right, so let's talk about each of
these stages.
So let's talk about the forming stage
first.
Now, the forming stage is a temporary
stage at the beginning, right?
And think of it as more of a meet and
greet type of stage.
A brief period right at the beginning.
People don't know one another.
So this team is just, as the name
suggests, forming.
People don't know one another.
people are introducing themselves.
Roles are completely unclear in this team.
You don't know what skill sets other team
members have.
They don't know what skill sets you have.
You don't know exactly
which of your skill sets
is going to play a
major part on this team.
And as I said, roles are unclear.
There might not be a lot of interaction
either.
Some people might be shy and not really
interacting.
So it's not really a cohesive team at this
point.
Now, there's a high dependence on the
leader, right?
So the team leader has been assigned and
everybody's focused on the leader.
The leader is giving instructions and
people are following those instructions.
People are asking questions of the leader,
right?
So they're relying on the leader for
guidance and direction, right, at this point.
Now, in an office environment,
then you're learning about the project,
you're learning about
your roles and about the
roles that you're going
to be interacting with.
So that's at the beginning, that's a
forming stage.
A certain amount of time goes by, the team
goes from the forming
to the storming stage.
And the key regarding the
storming stage is that team
members are trying to
establish themselves on the team.
They're trying to vie for position.
And your beginning, the team is beginning
to address the direction of the work.
the beginning to address the direction of
the team.
And at this stage now, there's a lot of
discussion going on.
There's a lot of health of discussion and
a lot of disagreements as well.
There might be a lot of conflicts.
Everyone's got their own ideas.
I think we should take this approach.
No, we need to take this approach.
Someone else comes along and says,
no, we need to take this other approach.
So we're all discussing ideas in the
storming stage.
The team is discussing ideas.
We've all got their own different ideas,
the different approaches.
So there's going to be a lot of
disagreements, a lot of conflicts.
There might even be some fighting and
arguing in breaking out.
And in fact, sometimes the storming stage
might be referred to
as the conflict stage.
There's going to be some competition.
Maybe, you know, a healthy competition
between team members, right?
But there's a lot of discussion about the
direction.
Now, a certain amount
of time goes by, the team
then goes from the
storming to the norming stage.
And the key here now is that the team,
or the project stabilises.
Team members are beginning to work
together.
That is the biggest key regarding the
norming stage.
They are beginning to work together.
Those arguments have died down.
Team members have come to a consensus.
They've all agreed, all right,
this is a direction of the work.
Everyone has agreed to that, all this is
what we are working towards now.
All those discussions have died down and,
you know, you've come to this consensus.
Also, roles and responsibilities are a lot
clearer now.
The clearer they've been accepted.
So you know exactly what decisions you can
make, at least small decisions,
you know what you can make.
Larger decisions, you're either going to
be careful to bring the whole group
together or at least bring subsections of
the group together to
make a larger decision.
So at this stage now, you are
beginning to make decisions on
what's best for the project as
opposed to what's best for you.
And because you're working together,
you basically sussed everyone out now.
You know who your friends are on the team,
you know who your enemies are on the team,
you know who you can trust, who you can't
trust.
This is kind of like the norming stage.
And then the team goes from
the norming to the performing stage
and the performing stage
now it's a well functioning unit.
Well functioning team roles are completely
clear.
You know exactly what decisions other
people can be making.
You're all working together.
You all understand each other's working
habits, team members are making decisions
on what's best for their team,
what's best for the project, not
necessarily what's best for them
individually.
And team members again are working
together as a productive team.
If there's one team member or
one team that's falling behind,
you've got the other team
that's pulling them back up.
It's like they all saying, we either fail
as a team or we succeed as a team.
So people are not
looking out for themselves,
are looking out for the team as a whole.
So that's the performing stage.
And then you have the adjourning stage,
which is a breakup of the team.
So the project has been, the goals have
been accomplished.
Or they haven't been accomplished.
It might have been cancelled.
Project might be cancelled, but it's a
breakup of the team and
the team now moves on.
So those are the five basic stages then of
the Tuckman model.
Now one very common aspect of this,
or one very very common question that's
often asked is what happens if a new team
member joins?
Well, regardless of where you are,
the team could be in the performing stage.
If a new team member
joins, the entire team
is going to go back to the forming stage.
The whole team is going
to go back to forming
and then go through those stages again.
Of course, the timeline is going to be a
lot less, right?
It might only be, you know, a few days or
a few hours even, right?
A couple of days or a few hours,
right?
But the entire team is going
to go back to the forming
stage and then go through
all of these stages again.
Now, something to bear in mind with this.
When we're talking about the
team going back to the forming
stage because of the new
team member joining, right?
This isn't referring to
things like, you know, the
work needs to be redistributed
or anything like that.
It's not talking about the work.
Team members are doing the work that they
need to do.
They're still doing all of that work.
That's not what it's referring to.
What this is referring to is team
interaction.
The entire team is going to go back to the
forming stage because
of this new team member.
It's talking about team interaction.
Think about this.
Just one team member, the
addition of one team member,
can completely change the
dynamics of the team sometimes.
So, you know, let's say you've got a team,
you know, they're at the performing stage.
They're working.
Right?
There might not be, you know, they're
interacting with each other.
They're working well.
You know, the team is performing.
They're performing well,
they're within budget on
timeline, they're doing the
work that they need to do.
But there's not a huge
amount of, you know,
say, social interaction
between team members.
Now, they're just doing the work.
A new team member joins.
A new team member comes in, you know, very
sociable and just brings
everybody together.
And now the team, the entire team is now
working.
The entire team is now socializing,
whereas they weren't socializing before.
That's just a very, very simple example.
You know, one team member can completely
change the entire dynamics of the team.
So, regardless of where you are,
the addition of a new team member,
the entire team goes
back to the forming stage
and then goes through
all of these stages again.
Also, another consideration to make when
we're talking about projects, remember a
project by definition is a beginning and
an end.
And on a project, especially on a
predictive project, you don't have
necessarily your entire
team from the beginning of
the project all the way
until the end of the project.
Team members are coming and going as and
when required.
So you're constantly going through these
stages.
A new team member joins because they
needed.
At this point, they roll onto the project.
You go back to the forming stage.
Right.
They do the work.
Another team member leaves.
Another team member joins.
Again, you're going through the stages.
Then you suddenly go back to forming
again.
So you don't always have to get to the
performing stage.
Not every team member.
will always always get to the performing
stage.
You might be stuck in one of the other
stages.
So that's another consideration to make.
So this was then the basic
principles, regarding the Tuckman
model, or the Tuckman
Ladder, as it's sometimes called.